<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE file SYSTEM "file:xml/file.dtd">
<file title="Authors">

  <chap title="Thom-Thom">
    <text>
      Liquid War rules have been invented by
      Thomas Colcombet.
    </text>
    <text>
      He was trying to find algorithms to find the shortest path
      from one point to another, and found the Liquid War
      algorithm. Then it came to his mind that a game could
      be build upon this algorithm, and Liquid War was born.
      He programmed the first two versions of Liquid War
      using Borland Pascal for DOS, and gave me some information
      about the algorithm so that I could re-program it.
    </text>
  </chap>

  <chap title="U-Foot">
    <text>
      I'm the guy who programmed the latest versions of Liquid War.
      I enhanced the algorithms, and did quite a bunch of work
      to have the game playable by (almost) anyone, that's to
      say create a correct GUI.
    </text>
    <text>
      If you want to join me, here's all the information you'll ever need:
    </text>
    <code>
Christian Mauduit

E-mail: "ufoot@ufoot.org" 
Web site: "http://www.ufoot.org"

GnuPG public key: FD409E94 - "http://www.ufoot.org/gnupg.pub"
GnuPG fingerprint: 4762 1EBA 5FA3 E62F 299C  B0BB DE3F 2BCD FD40 9E94

Snail mail: 32 rue Jean Moulin  95100 Argenteuil  FRANCE
    </code>
  </chap>

  <chap title="Other contributors">
    <text>
      As Liquid War is now free software, protected by the GPL,
      anyone is allowed to view, edit, modify, re-compile
      the source code, and distribute it, as long as Liquid 
      War is still distributed under the GPL.
    </text>
    <text>
      Here's a list of the contributors:
    </text>
    <list>
      <elem>
	Alstar: drew a map, which is now included in the main distribution.
      </elem>
      <elem>
        Peter Wang: ported Liquid War to GNU/Linux.
      </elem>
      <elem>
	Cort Danger Stratton : helped me setting up network support.
      </elem>
      <elem>
	Tim Chadburn : wrote midi files for the game. His contribution has
	been truely appreciated since it's rather hard to find GNU GPL
	compliant artwork. He also wrote documentation and helped with
	midi support in general.
      </elem>
      <elem>
        Jan Gretschuskin : contributed 11 maps, and made the German
	translation. So if you run Liquid War with German menus, you
	know who you have to thank -> Jan! 8-) 
	Also do not forget to visit "http://www.game-factor.de"
      </elem>
      <elem>
        Mouse : contributed a map.
      </elem>
      <elem>
        Rene Stach : drew 3 maps.
      </elem>
      <elem>
	Roderick Schertler : implemented HTTP 1.1 support.
      </elem>
      <elem>
	Ryan D. Brown : ported Liquid War to Mac OS X.
      </elem>
      <elem>
	Eduard Bloch : maintained the Debian package, 
	and helped with German support.
      </elem>
      <elem>
	Michael Terry : provided a .desktop file for better integration
	with Gnome, KDE and other UNIX desktop environments.
      </elem>
      <elem>
	Kasper Hviid : contributed many maps, with their own
	textures, and made the Danish translation. Great work, also
	available on "http://levels.2v1.cz/index.html"
      </elem>
      <elem>
	David Redick : wrote an external random map generator,
	available on "http://xdavidx.sqrville.org/lwmapgen/index.html"
      </elem>
      <elem>
	Alexandre Pineau : maintains the Debian package.
      </elem>
      <elem>
	Michael Wagner : translated the web site in German.
      </elem>
      <elem>
	Peter Williams : fixed the "too many opened socket" server bug.
      </elem>
      <elem>
	Jan Samohyl : submitted strategy tips.
      </elem>
      <elem>
	Gavin : wrote the Liquid War fanfic.
      </elem>
      <elem>
	Dave Vasilevsky : fixed the Mac OS X port.
      </elem>
      <elem>
	2 of omega : contributed a map.
      </elem>
      <elem>
	666-REFIZUL-666 : created many maps (distributed separately).
      </elem>
      <elem>
	Thomas Klausner : fixed Makefile for FreeBSD
      </elem>
      <elem>
	Joan Dolc : helped with Mac OS/X port
      </elem>
      <elem>
        Jan Szenborn : Polish translation.
      </elem>
    </list>
    <text>
      Many other people helped me by submitting bug reports and patches,
      and I want to thank them for their precious help. Thanks to all the
      Debian people too, who nicely maintain the Liquid War .deb package.
    </text>
  </chap>

</file>
