<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE file SYSTEM "file:xml/file.dtd">
<file title="Bugs">

  <chap title="Report a new bug">
    <text>
      If you have troubles with Liquid War 5,
      if you think it is a bug,
      and if it is not described in this file, then just
      send a (precise...) decription of your problem
      to the Liquid War user mailing list.
    </text>
    <text>
      Besides, it happens that now most bug reports come from
      the Debian tracking system
      "http://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/pkgreport.cgi?pkg=liquidwar".
      Thanks to the Debian users and maintainers, it's a very
      valuable feedback source.
    </text>
    <text>
      Additionnaly, on online bug tracking system is availalable
      on "https://github.com/ufoot/liquidwar5/issues".
      I try to collect everything here : bugs reported on the mailing-list,
      bugs from Debian, and bugs I found myself. Alternatively
      you can report bugs directly on it 8-)
    </text>
  </chap>

  <chap title="Network">
    <text>
      Network support in Liquid War is far from being perfect, so there
      are a bunch of little problems which can appear. Basically, once
      the game is correctly started on a LAN, you should have no problems,
      but getting the game started might be difficult.
    </text>
  </chap>

  <chap title="Mouse does not work">
    <text>
      Some users reported that they were unable to control the Liquid War
      cursor with the mouse. Well, the answer is a typical Microsoftish
      "this ain't a bug, it's a feature!".
    </text>
    <text>
      More seriously, you're supposed to move the cursor with the keyboard
      in Liquid War. There's no way to handle the cursor "like a mouse pointer"
      (*). This is due to:
    </text>
    <list>
      <elem>
	Severe limitations in the Liquid War core algorithm.
      </elem>
      <elem>
	The fact that moving the cursor "too fast" would really change the
	gameplay of Liquid War. As a Liquid War integrist 8-) I can tell you
	the game would really not be the same if you could move the cursor
	as fast as you wish. It's part of the game that sometimes it takes
	you ages to recover from a strategical mistakes. You need to think
	twice before going to the very end of a level. That's strategy.
	At least that's how I view things... Anyways as I mentionned above
	there's a limitation in the core algorithm.
      </elem>
    </list>
    <text>
      (*) This is not perfectly true, there's a way to control the cursor
      with the mouse, but it's designed for the case "4 people want to play
      on the same computer and one single keyboard is not enough".
      Controlling the cursor with the mouse in Liquid War is possible but
      yet rather hard to master 8-/ Try it and you'll understand what I mean.
      This mode can be set up in the "Teams" menu.
    </text>
  </chap>

  <chap title="Game does not start">
    <text>
      On non UNIX platforms such as Windows or DOS, Liquid War
      is distributed in a .zip file. It's IMPORTANT that you
      unzip the .zip files with an "unzipper" which preserves
      the directory structure. Most install problems under
      Windows come from broken unzipping programs which extract
      all files in the same directory... WinZip 8.x or the unzip32.exe
      utility that comes with DJGPP are both able to uncompress
      Liquid War .zip files correctly.
    </text>
    <text>
      On Liquid War 5.5.9 and later, the Windows version should detect
      this problem automatically and warn you with a message which
      basically says something like "Unable to load datafile.
      Are you sure Liquid War is correctly installed?".
      If you get this message, you need to reinstall the game by
      unzipping it with a "correct" unzipping program which does
      not wreck directory structrure up.
    </text>
  </chap>

  <chap title="Datafile bugs">
    <text>
      Sometimes there are some problems when compiling the datafile,
      this includes:
    </text>
    <list>
      <elem>
        The liquidwarcol, liquidwarmap and liquidwartex utilities
	might freeze or segfault. Typing "make" again often solves
	the problem.
      </elem>
      <elem>
        The background image sometimes ends up using the wrong palette,
	which has a very nasty consequence: it looks ugly.
      </elem>
    </list>
    <text>
      These bugs are quite hard to get rid off, since I can not
      reproduce them easily. The good solution would be to completely
      rewrite the liquidwarcol, liquidwarmap and liquidwartex utilities.
    </text>
  </chap>

  <chap title="Midi does not work on OSS">
    <part title="Preamble">
      <text>
	IF your midi music on Liquid War, or indeed any other
	Allegro game, doesn't work and you are using the OSS
	(Open Sound System) drivers (these are the sound drivers
	which come with the standard kernel distribution), this may
	well be because Allegro only supports "FM synthesis"
	and not "wavetable" when it is using OSS. FM synthesis
	is a very old method of making sound from MIDI and
	has long since been replaced by wavetable synthesis, with the net
	result that it's quite possible you've got OSS MIDI
	working nicely in other applications without having FM
	support set up at all. This is what I found. (It has
	to be said that I didn't find the FM sound quality quite as bad
	as people have said, though).
      </text>
      <text>
	In this situation, it looks to me like you have the following choices:
      </text>
    </part>
    <part title="Hack Allegro...">
      <text>
	...to implement wavetable midi on OSS :-)
      </text>
      <text>
	and for the rest of us...
      </text>
    </part>
    <part title="Use Allegro's DIGMID midi driver...">
      <text>
	...which creates audio from MIDI using a set of patches
	(more info here: "http://www.talula.demon.co.uk/allegro/digmid.html")
	and plays back through your sound card's audio.
      </text>
    </part>
    <part title="Get an FM driver up and running...">
      <text>
	...Which is comprised of the following steps:
      </text>
      <list>
	<elem>
	  Find out which FM driver is appropriate for your sound card.
          If you have distribution-specific tools and docs for setting up sound, try those.
          If not, you will need to be familiar with the knowledge in the Sound-HOWTO and
          Kernel-HOWTO i.e. know how to compile kernels and modules and deal with sound
          drivers.
	</elem>
	<elem>
	  Look through the OSS modules in 'make menuconfig' and see if anything
          catches your eye. See if there is any specific documentation on your sound card on
          "http://www.linuxdoc.org". Do a few web searches. For my AWE64, I use the OPL3 driver.
	</elem>
	<elem>
	  Compile and install the FM driver module, or set up your system to use the new
          kernel if you want to compile the driver in.
	</elem>
	<elem>
	  Load the module, or boot your new kernel. It is very important that you pay
          attention to what is said in the 'help' for your FM driver in 'make menuconfig'
          and read any necessary files in the Documentation/sound/ directory. For example,
          I just had a nice half-hour wondering why the hell my FM wasn't working now when
          it had been before - with the OPL3 driver, you have to give the option io=0x388
          to insmod. Which is stated nice and clear in the docs, but of course I had forgotten
          since then. You can prevent such happenings by recording options permanently in
          /etc/modules.conf - see the manpage etc.
	</elem>
	<elem>
	  Try the game. If it's worked you will hear particularly beepy music. Enjoy!
	</elem>
      </list>
    </part>
    <part title="Opl3 occult FAQ">
      <text>
	--IMPORTANT-- If you are using Liquid War, your FM will only work if you go to the
	map 'Elephant inside a boa' and proceed to chase each other round in circles for at
	least 10 minutes. This cures a bug in the design of the OPL3 interface which
	conflicts badly with the core Liquid War algorithms. How the hell the music hardware
	even knows about the core algorithms I don't know, but that's what I made of the
	now-defunct opl3-occult-FAQ, from which here is an excerpt:
      </text>
      <code>
	Many roads a man must take. Those with one-track minds are DOOMED, I tells ya.
      </code>
      <text>
	----  The Liquid War algorithm calculates distances to one place, the cursor.
      </text>
      <text>
	And:
      </text>
      <code>
	Man or machine, face or code, must stand strong and solid; must not just ooze away as slime.
      </code>
      <text>
	---- We think it might just take objection to the whole 'slimy' nature of the LW
	beings. As well as it being LIQUID War.
      </text>
      <text>
	So, our carefully tailored approach, is to firstly have the players going in all
	the possible different directions evenly by moving around the map in circles, and
	secondly to divert the opl3's attention from the general slimy liquidness of it all
	by emphasizing the solidity, reality, and natural goodness of that classic
	tapestry: an elephant inside a boa.
      </text>
      <text>
	That and it's a f***ing ace level.
      </text>
    </part>
  </chap>

  <chap title="Checksum errors">
    <text>
      The Liquid War server is a "light" servers which - to some extent -
      has no idea about what is going on in the game. It simply replicates
      key strokes between clients and each client maintains its own
      game state. Normally, the game is designed so that given the same
      user input, it will behave exactly the same.
    </text>
    <text>
      However, it happens that sometimes 2 clients can behave differently,
      and this is a (severe) bug. One consequence is that messages reporting
      "Checksum errors" appear on the server's and on the client's console
      output. This bug appears when using non-default rules settings.
      Basically, if someones tweaks his rules, then the checksum errors appear.
      Of course I double-triple checked that options were correctly sent on the
      network, but, well, could not fix the bug. Yet. The short term solution
      seems to play with default factory settings...
    </text>
    <text>
      I'm highly interested in bug-reports concerning this problem.
    </text>
  </chap>

</file>
